Guide to Mary Purchase papers, [ca. 1937-1988].
Purchase, Mary papers, [ca. 1937-1988].
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Mary Purchase Papers, [ca. 1937-1988].
23-19-3201
Mary Elizabeth Purchase.
1 cubic ft.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes correspondence, publications, awards, and studies concerning Mary Purchase's career and her work on detergents, water quality, laundry, consumers and the economy.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of Textiles and Apparel, Cornell University.
Mary Purchase came to Cornell in 1945 as a graduate student in chemistry, having earned a bachelor's degree from Eastern Michigan University in education and mathematics. After completing her master' degree, she was an instructor for three years in the Department of Household Economics and Management in the College of Home Economics. In 1951, she left Cornell for Iowa State University, where she earned a Ph.D. in household equipment and chemistry in 1957.
She returned to Cornell in 1961 as an associate professor in the Department of Household Economics and Management. In 1969 she served as graduate faculty representative and department extension leader in the newly formed Department of Design and Environmental Analysis. In 1973, Dr. Purchase was named professor and with the 1985 reorganization, became a member of the Department of Textiles and Apparel. She retired in 1986 and became emeritus professor that same year.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence, publications, awards, and studies concerning Mary Purchase's career and her work on detergents, water quality, laundry, consumers and the economy.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Purchase, Mary Elizabeth.; Cornell University--Faculty.
Subjects:
Washing machines.; Consumers--United States.; Laundry.; Water Quality.; Detergents--Environmental aspects.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Publications
Boxes 1, Folders 1-5
Series II. Projects/Studies
Boxes 1, Folders 6-13
Series III. Conferences/Workshops
Boxes 1, Folders 14-21
Series IV. Correspondence
Boxes 1, Folders 22-45
Series V. Awards
Boxes 1
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Publications
  - Articles, 1950-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Articles, 1972-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Articles, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Memos, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Articles, Memos Written by Mary Purchase, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
- Series II. Projects/Studies
  - Detergent-Phosphorus — information verification project, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Detergent-Phosphate Ban Controversy — summary report, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Detergent-Phosphate Ban-Virginia, North Carolina, Wisconsin, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Detergent Ban — "Consumer Costs Associated with Detergent Phosphate Bans" report by Proctor and Gamble, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Home Economists' submissions to the International Joint Commission, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Detergent Legislation, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Research report for Proctor and Gamble, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Clay Soil Study, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Residual Soil on Laundered Fabric - Hatch #280, no date (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Series III. Correspondence/Workshops
  - In-service conference-"Consumers and the Economy", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Conference - "Consumer and the Economy", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Food Editors Conference, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Human Ecology Institute- "Energy: Consumer Policy", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Workshop- "Cooking with Microwaves", 1978, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Symposium — Third Domestic Water Quality, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Toward a Philosophy of Home Management"- sponsored by United States Office of Education - Penn State, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - National Secretaries Association Presentation, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Series IV. Correspondence
  - General, 1983-07-1984-06 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - General, 1982-07-1983-06 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - General, 1981-07-1982-06 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - General, 1980-07-1981-06 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - General, 1979-07-1980-06 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - General, 1978-07-1979-06 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - General, 1977-07-1978-06 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - General, 1975-07-1976-06 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - General, 1973-07-1974-06 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - General, 1972-07-1973-06 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - General, 1971-07-1972-06 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence concerning detergents, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - General, 1969-07-1970-06 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - General, 1968-07-1969-06 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - General, 1966-07-1967-06 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - General, 1965-07-1966-06 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - General, 1964-07-1965-06 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - General, 1963-07-1964-06 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence concerning Electrolux, Maytag, Whirlpool, 1975-1984 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence concerning dishwashers, dryers, freezers, refrigerators, 1947-1972 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence concerning detergents, 1937-1974 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence concerning dust, equipment selection, finishes on fabric, home management and hoods, 1946-1971 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence concerning housecleaning, humidifiers, irons, laundering, metal cleaning, microwave ovens, odors and ranges, 1949-1973 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence concerning shampooing, soap, stain removal, testing products, vacuum cleaners, water softeners, 1948-1972 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Series V. Awards
  - ASTM- fellow — Recognition of exceptional leadership and acute technical and editorial insights and for diplomatic recommendations that bring together opposing points of view which were major contributions to the progress of F-11, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Caricature of Mary - done for her retirement (Folder 1)